Guide to the Frederick Bedell Papers, 1891-1984.
Bedell,Frederick papers, 1891-1984.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Frederick Bedell papers, 1891-1984.
14-22-2190
Frederick Bedell, 1868-1958.
4.2 cubic ft.
Correspondence, notes, drawings, files, papers, volumes, news clippings.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Correspondence, notes, and drawings relating to hearing and devices for the deaf; files on the oscilloscope; files relating to his student work at Yale, his teaching career at Cornell, and his subsequent research at California Institute of Technology.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Professor of physics.
Frederick Bedell received an A.B. degree from Yale University in 1890 and a Ph.D degree from Cornell in 1892. He was appointed Assistant Professor of Physics at Cornell in 1893, and, in 1904, Professor of Applied Electricity. His most important contributions in electrical engineering were his experimental investigations and theoretical studies delaing with alternating currents. In 1917, he was appointed as an advisor in the establishment at Cornell of one of the United States Army Schools of Military Aeronautics which led to his work in the investigation of airplane performance and design. He also worked on the development of devices to aid the deaf by utilizing the phenomenon of sound conduction through the bones. For twenty-nine years he served as editor of the Physical Review. After his retirement, he did research at California Institute of Technology. Frederick Bedell died in 1958.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Correspondence, notes, and drawings relating to hearing and devices for the deaf; files on the oscilloscope; files relating to his student work at Yale, his teaching career at Cornell, and his subsequent research at California Institute of Technology; correspondence files; personal and family papers; and bound volumes including biographical papers, reprints, news clippings, and patents. Also Modern Gypsies, by Mary Crehore Bedell.
Bibliography of publications by Bedell including papers, theses, and charts.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Bedell, Frederick, 1868-1958.; California Institute of Technology.; Cornell University. Department of Physics.; Yale University--Students.
Subjects:
Physics--Study and teaching.; Hearing.; Hearing aids.; Bone conduction.; Oscilloscopes.; Electric measurements.; Electricity--Experiments.; Electric currents, alternating.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Report of part of the Short Electric Railway System, Rochester, 1891 (book) (Box 1, Folder 1)
- An Electric Elevator (Bedell's first invention) (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Mechanism of the ear (model) (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Hearing (Box 1, Folder 4)
- The Mechanism of Hearing (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Memo on hearing (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Hearing, original drawings (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Hearing notes; Talk given at Cornell, CIT, others (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Hearing in animals (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Hearing in birds (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Cat's ear (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Bone conduction dictograph (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Bone conductor hearing aid, photos (Box 1, Folder 13)
- News clippings on "Deaf Speaker" bone conduction hearing aid (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Bone conduction patent-assignment to Dictograph (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Letters to the Burts re Dictograph, Oct. 3, 1930-Feb. 27, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Dictograph - decisions, settlements, contract, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Bibliography, 1892-1900 (see accession folder for detailed list) (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Oscilloscope and voltage-regulating auto-transformer (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1926-1928 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Reprints (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Orders, 1929-1930 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Sales (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Correspondence re General Radio purchase of oscilloscope and transformer patents (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Patent infringement suit of General Radio against DuMont Lab (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Court cases - press clippings (Box 2, Folder 8)
- T.V. gift oscilloscope (Box 2, Folder 9)
- DuMont recommended for Edison Medal, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Miscellaneous, including alternating current dictionary, "unit" book contracts (Box 2, Folder 11)
- AAAS - American Association for the Advancement of Science (Box 3, Folder 1)
- AIEE - American Institute of Electric Engineers (Box 3, Folder 2)
- AIEE - Vancouver paper, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- American Institute of Physics (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Eta Kappa Nu Association (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Physical Society (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Societies (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Thomas Alva Edison Foundation (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Papers by Bedell fellow workers (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Papers by Bedell (reprints) (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Special reprints by friends I (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Special reprints by friends II (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Miscellaneous science articles (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Letters re Bedell's books (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Caltech - General (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Caltech - Mt. Wilson, Palomar, news clips (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Caltech - Millikan news clips (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Cornell University - Official, appointments and retirement, thesis (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Cornell University - History of physics, founding of AAAS and Physical Society, Ernest Merritt letters (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Cornell in Pictures, 1868-1954 (book) (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Yale University - General (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Yale University - Early professors, biographical sketches of Nichols, Merritt, Moler (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, A-C (Box 5, Folder 1)
  Allen, Frank; Bailey, W.B.; Ballard, William C.; Baitsell, G.A.; Baver, L.D.; Berry, Romeyn; Blaker, Adelaide; Blair, William L.; Brandow, Baird; Buckley, Oliver; Cal. Inst. Tech. (Bacher, R); Cal. Inst. Tech.; Caroline (Thomas), Crehore, Albert
- Correspondence, F-Joh (Box 5, Folder 2)
  Fact and Publication; FBI; Fite, William B.; Ford, Henry (1929 letters); Goldsmith, Norris; Goldsmith, Thomas; Grantham (prof.); Hartman, Paul; Holmes, George; Horne, Harley; Johnson, J. Kelly
- Correspondence, J (Box 5, Folder 3)
  Joslin, Elliot
- Correspondence, K-M (Box 5, Folder 4)
  King, A.A.; Kirkpatrick, Paul; Kuhn, Jack; Lahens; Lennox, William; Lohman, Ralph; Librarian, Cornell U.; Lyons, Helen; Marshall; Matey, George; Maxstadt, Francais; Maerritt Family; Millikan, Robert; Morey, Dan; Mueller, George; Murdock Carlton
- Correspondence (Box 5, Folder 5)
  Lorentz, H.A.
- Correspondence, N-R (Box 5, Folder 6)
  Needham, J.C.; Neher, Victor; Noyes, Bradford; Overal, Edward A.; Pasadena; Pasadena Presbyterian Church; Piersan, Albert; Reich, Herbert J.; Richards, Lorenzo; Ries, Donald; Ries, Heinrich; Rivers, Ruth and Tom
- Correspondence, S-Z (Box 5, Folder 7)
  Scott, Merit; Strong, John; Swann, W.F.G.; Utereiner, Ray; Who's Who in America; White, William; Wilcox, W.F.; Zeiger, Franklin
- Pensions (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Income Tax Returns, 1847-1951 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Annuities (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Photographs (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Photographs (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Award, "Modern Pioneer of the American Frontiers of Industry," Feb. 16, 1940 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Bibliography (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Biography - F. Bedell and Mary Crehore Bedell, includes genealogy (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Correspondence re move to Pasadena, 1937 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Early recollections, school records (Box 6, Folder 5)
- 80th birthday, acknowledgements, ode by F.B. Hirsch (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Family miscellaneous (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Graduate students (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Health and exercise (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Integrals - early notes (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Memorabilia (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Miscellaneous - some fun, some wisdom (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Papers re estate of Edwin F. Bedell (father) (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Personal miscellaneous (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Personal miscellaneous, guest and address books (Box 7, Folder 4)
- 1938 wedding announcement (Box 7, Folder 5)
- School compositions, 1877-1883 (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Correspondence, 1880-1886 (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1887-1890 (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1891-1896 (Box 7, Folder 9)
- Correspondence, 1896-1897 (Box 7, Folder 10)
- Correspondence, 1897-1907 (Box 7, Folder 11)
- Correspondence, 1810-1952 (Box 7, Folder 12)
- Vols. 1-7, Biographical papers, reprints, news clippings, patents, etc. of Frederick Bedell (see accession folder for detailed list) (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Modern Gypsies, by Mary Crehore Bedell (Box 8, Folder 2)
- "Magnetism of Iron and the Magnetic Circuit," a collection of notes, 1894 (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Publications mainly by F. Bedell, 1892-1949 (see accession folder for detailed list) (Box 9, Folder 1)